Guide to the Lena Morrow Lewis Papers TAM.015
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Lena Morrow Lewis Papers
1899-1951
TAM.015
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
2.0 linear feet (5 boxes)
Lena Morrow Lewis was a socialist activist in California and Alaska, a candidate for public office, journalist, editor of The Labor World, and worked for the release of Warren K. Billings who had been imprisoned for complicity in the July 1916 Preparedness Day parade bomb explosion in San Francisco. The papers contain correspondence, scrapbooks, unpublished writings, memorabilia and ephemera. NOTE: the collection has been microfilmed (with the exception of a few files), and researchers must use the microfilm copy (R-7124, reels 63-65).
Lewis, Lena Morrow
Box 1-5
Provenance
Transfer from Rand School Archives, 1962 and gift of Margaret K. Wilson, 1974.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions, however, researchers must use the microfilm copy (Film R-7124, Reels 63-65), with the exception of a few files that were not microfilmed (Box 1, Folder 8; Box 3, Folder 12; Box 5, Folders 2 & 3).
Historical/Biographical Note
Lena Morrow Lewis was one of the most active women socialists in the United States during the first half of the 20th century. Throughout her career in radical politics, Lewis was immersed in a variety of socialist activities. She was a candidate on the Socialist Party ticket in numerous local, state, and congressional elections in California and Alaska. Besides her electoral endeavors, Lewis gave lectures on contemporary socialist issues and worked as a journalist for several socialist and labor publications in California and Alaska, including The Labor World, which she edited. Lewis also worked diligently in support of the release of Warren K. Billings who, along with Tom Mooney, was convicted and imprisoned for 23 years on a charge of complicity in the Preparedness Day parade bomb explosion at San Francisco in July 1916.
Scope and Content Note
The Lena Morrow Lewis Papers, 1899-1951, are organized into 20 subject files, including Billings correspondence, general correspondence, family and personal papers, lectures, memorabilia, memorials and biographical notes, notebook, notes, photographs, printed matter, radio talks, and nine scrapbooks. Each subject file has been given a frame number (i.e., XVII:1, where the roman numeral XVII indicates that the Lewis Papers are the 17th collection within the microfilm publication Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956). A list of the subject files and some of the items within specific files can be found in the complete reel list which follows this description of the arrangement of the collection.
The Billings correspondence (XVII:1) and the general correspondence (XVII:2) constitute the largest quantity of materials in this collection. The letters within these two subject files are arranged in chronological order, with undated items placed at the end of each file. Of special importance in the correspondence files is the extensive collection of letters from and about Warren K. Billings during 17 of his,23 years in prison. The letters, which are occasionally critical. of Tom Mooney, affirm Billings' innocence and concentrate on the numerous efforts to have him released from prison. The general correspondence includes numerous letters discussing contemporary political issues and socialist personalities. Much of this correspondence is from less prominent socialists, but there are letters from such important figures as Theodore Debs, James H. Maurer, James Oneal, Eugene V. Debs, Norman Thomas, and Charles Edward Russell. In this file, there are also a number of personal letters from Iva Ettor which offer some interesting insights into some of the socialist and labor organizing activities of her husband, Joe Ettor.
There are 27 photographs contained in the Lewis Papers (XVII:9). The photographs are arranged in chronological order and include both portraits of Lena Morrow Lewis and group photographs featuring Lewis and other socialists. Each photograph has been labeled with a number in the lower right hand corner of the picture. These numbers correspond with the description of the photographs in the complete reel list. (After being microfilmed, the photographs were separated to the Library’s Photograph collection (see Separated Materials, below).
The nine scrapbooks (XVII:12 XVII:20) constitute another important segment of this collection. These scrapbooks, which consist primarily of newspaper clippings, focus upon specific aspects of Lewis, life, particularly her work with husband, Arthur Morrow Lewis; her experiences as a journalist and political candidate in Alaska; her involvement with the Socialist Party in California; and her writings about various personalities in the socialist and communist movements. Each scrapbook has been provided with an index which lists the title of each article, the page number(s) where each article is located, and the author of the article if the author is known. For each scrapbook, the index was filmed before the contents of the scrapbook.
There is also a variety of miscellaneous items in this collection. Prominent among these items are a small number of WEVD radio scripts (XVII:11) and speech notes (XVII:8) which pertain to Lewis' involvement with the Social Democratic Federation. Some interesting items are also contained in the memorabilia file (XVII:5), such as lecture announcements, Socialist Party dues books, a ticket to the International Socialist Congress at Copenhagen in 1910, a resignation card from the American Federation of Labor, and a certificate of nomination for the 22nd Assembly District of California.
Arrangement
Folders are generally arranged topically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Inventory
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Lena Morrow Lewis Photographs (Photographs 43).
Separated Material
Lena Morrow Lewis Photographs (Photographs 43)
Microfilm
This collection is available on microfilm (Film R-7124, Reels 63-65) for use in this repository only. Researchers must use microfilm for this collection. The following files have not been microfilmed: Box 1, Folder 8; Box 3, Folder 12; Box 5, Folders 2 & 3.
Billings, Warren K., 1893-1972; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926; Debs, Theodore, 1864-1945; Ettor, Iva; Ettor, Joseph J.; Lewis, Arthur M. (Arthur Morrow), b. 1873; Maurer, James H. (James Hudson), b. 1864.; Mooney, Thomas J., 1882-1942.; Oneal, James, b. 1875.; Russell, Charles Edward, 1860-1941; Social Democratic Federation of America.; Socialist Party of California.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; WEVD (Radio station) New York, N.Y.; Alaska |x Politics and government.; Black-and-white photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Communism |z United States; Scrapbooks.; Scripts (documents).; Socialism |z United States.; Speeches.
- Billings Correspondence, February 19, 1922-December 11, 1939, nd
  - Billings Correspondence, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    R-7124, Reel 63; Frame XVII:1
  - Billings Correspondence, 1925-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Billings Correspondence, 1930-1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Billings Correspondence, 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Billings Correspondence, Jan 1939-Jun 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Billings Correspondence, Jul 1939-Dec 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 63; Frame XVII:1
  - Billings Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Billings Correspondence: copies of letters, chiefly billings, 1929-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    not Filmed
- Correspondence, January 9, 1905-May 28, 1951, nd
  - Correspondence, 1905-1919 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 64; Frame XVII:2
  - Correspondence, 1920-1924 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1929 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1934 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Family and Personal Papers, Oct 2, 1906-May 31, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:3
  - Lectures, 1903-1944, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:4
  - Memorabilia, 1903-1947, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:5
  - Memorials and Biographical Notes, 1947, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:6
  - Notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:7
  - Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:8
- Photographs
  Scope and Contents note
  Note: The photographs, listed below, which were reproduced on the microfilm, have been separated to the Library's Photograph collection (collection number: Tamiment Photographs 43)
  - List of photographs: 1. Mary A. Story, mother of Lena Morrow Lewis, nd. 2. Lena Morrow Lewis as a young child, nd. 3. Lena Morrow Lewis as a young woman, nd. 4. Lena Morrow Lewis arriving in Seattle, Washington, Lena Morrow Lewis arriving in Seattle, Washington, 1905. The man at the left is unidentified. 1905. The man at the left is unidentified. 5. L R, standing: unidentified, J. G. Phelps Stokes, Victor Berger, Clarence Darrow, and two unidentified people, 1907. Rose Pastor Stokes is one of the women seated in front. 6. Delegates attending the International Socialist Congress in Copenhagen, 1910. 7. Part of the parade procession at the International Socialist Congress in Copenhagen, 1910. 8. Part of the parade procession at the International Socialist Congress in Copenhagen, 1910. 9. Part of the crowd attending a "Votes for Women" rally in Lynn, Massachusetts, 1911. 10. Part of the crowd attending a "Votes for Women" rally in Lynn, Massachusetts, 1911. 11. Jim Carey sitting on the speaker's platform with Lena Morrow Lewis, Lynn, Massachusetts, 1911. 12. Jim Carey listening to a speech by Lena Morrow Lewis in Lynn, Massachusetts, 1911. 13. Lena Morrow Lewis in Alaska, ca. 1912. 14. Lena Morrow Lewis in her Alaskan garden, ca. 1912. 15. The Arctic Brotherhood in Dawson, Alaskan Territory, where Lena Morrow Lewis spoke in 1912 and 1914. 16. Lena Morrow Lewis, left, and Carrie Bush in Oakland, California, 1918 17. Some of the women employees in the national headquarters of the Socialist Party, Chicago, 1926. Lena Morrow Lewis is standing third from the left and Mabel Barnes is standing at the far left. 18. Lena Morrow Lewis, left, and an unidentified woman, nd. 19. Emmeline M. Dent, December 1928. 20. Lena Morrow Lewis, far right, and three unidentified women, nd. 21. Lena Morrow Lewis, far left, and Jasper McLevy, seated, in front, nd. 22. Lena Morrow Lewis, left, and an unidentified man, nd. 23. Lena Morrow Lewis in her later years, ca. 1940s. 24. L R; William Feigenbaum, James Oneal, and Ryan Walker, nd. 25. A group of Socialist Party women in Minneapolis, Minnesota, nd. 26. Dan Irving, nd., Dan Irving, nd. 27. Members of the English branch of the Socialist Party, Local Duluth, nd., ca.1905-1940 (Box - -, Folder - -)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:9
- Printed Matter
  - Printed Matter, contains: - Fosdick, Harry Emerson. The Unknown Soldier. Extension of Remarks of Hon. James P. Pope of Idaho in the Senate of the United States, Saturday, June 16, 1934. Washington, D.C.: U. S. Govt. Print. Office, 4 pp., 1934. - Story, Russell M. Growth Toward Effectiveness. Claremont, California! Pomona Collage, 11 pp., Sep 17, 1936. - Arnold, Mary Elliott and Reed, Mabel. Find Your Lobster. Cooperation in Nova Scotia, [4 pp], (193 )., ca.1934-1939 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:10
- Clippings and Scrapbooks
  - Radio Talks, Jul 1916-Aug 1943, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:11
  - Clippings, ca.1930-1940s (Box 3, Folder 12)
    not filmed
  - Scrapbook No. 1: Special Articles by and About Lena Morrow Lewis and Arthur Morrow Lewis, 1899-1941 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:12
  - Scrapbook No. 2: Alaska: Articles and Experiences, 1912-1917 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:13
  - Scrapbook No. 3: A Collection of Articles by Various Comrades: Stories of Personalities: A Book of Human Interest ... Note: this scrapbook, although microfilmed, is missing., 1920-1931 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:14
  - Scrapbook No. 4: Articles Pertaining to Communism and Activities of the Communist Party ...., 1925-1930 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:15
  - Scrapbook No. 5: Record of organizational Activities of the Socialist Party of California, 1925-1930 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:16
  - Scrapbook No. 6: Articles Appearing in The Labor World, 1925-1930 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:17
  - Scrapbook No. 7: Socialist Campaigns California, 1926, 1928, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:18
  - Scrapbook No. 8: Lena Morrow Lewis Early Socialist Activities, 1899-1922 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:19
  - Scrapbook No. 9, Articles on Lena Morrow Lewis and Socialism, 1904-1935 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 65; Frame XVII:20
  - Scrapbook, Untitled, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, envelopes, ephemera, 1930s-1940s (Box 5, Folder 3)